In this course, you have seen a lot of
different kinds of uh uses of LLMs. And
today, I'm going to emphasize the use of
LLMs as a tool of scientific and
mathematical discovery. And in
particular, there's going to be an
emphasis on the ability of LLMs to
discover abstract concepts and how this
can accelerate these uh discovery
processes. Okay. So uh let us dive in.
Let us start with u the problem of
mathematical discovery. This is of
course one of the grandest challenges uh
known to
humanity. Now um how does the process of
mathematical discovery look like? There
is the p the the process of modeling
where you are you know getting inspired
by some sort of a real world phenomenon
and then modeling it uh in terms of a
variety of definitions and and concepts.
Now once you have a set of definitions
at that point you may want to
conjecture various properties of these
definitions and then these are u you
know potentially candidate theorems and
lemas and then there is this process of
rigorous reasoning where you are
actually proving these statements and
this process is for human
mathematicians intrinsically social. you
are convincing each other about the the
rigor of your reasoning and the value of
your conjectures, right? But this
process just continues in this sort of
an iterative loop. Uh so you may have
you may see proofs and counter examples
and these may influence your models as
well as your conjectures and this
process just goes on. Right? That's how
the the um that's the history of
mathematics.
Now the dream of the field of AI for
math is that you want to automate uh
substantial pieces of this process and
as a result you want to accelerate this
process even more. You want to be able
to discover new kinds of math and um and
uh you know uh this includes settling
known conjectures but also potentially
coming up with new
conjectures. And then there is the the
setting of natural sciences that is also
going to be something I'll cover in this
lecture. And here uh unlike in math you
are engaging with the real
world. There is this process of theory
building where you're coming up with
hypothesis about the the universe and
then you are using uh these hypothesis
to design experiments and then you are
experimentally validating them right and
this experimental validation process
creates new data and then this data
leads to new kinds of theories uh for
example by refinement of the existing
hypothesis or in some cases you may want
to just come up with entirely new
concepts and and um new
predictions. So the ambition of the area
of AI for science is to automate
hypothesis generation and experiment
design.
Now the key ideas in the areas of AI for
math and AI for science at this point
are that number one search is a really
powerful concept and so we want to
imagine these uh spaces of hypothesis
conjectures and proofs and
systematically search
them. Now uh this is of course a very
massive space. There are all
these you know uh potential statements
about various mathematical objects and
there are all these hypotheses that are
possible in the universe and this space
is you know clearly infinite. Now um how
do you explore this space in a in a
tractable way? Well, you use prior
knowledge to prioritize directions of
search. And that's also how humans
proceed. We don't just do discovery in a
vacuum. We
read existing papers and uh sometimes we
incrementally advance on them and
sometimes we make a big leap. But that
prior knowledge is always of
value. But then also we learn from
experience how and how not to uh do this
sort of
exploration. You know you find out that
you made certain uh choices uh while
building your theory and then you find
that this just didn't work right. And
that's experience for you. And then you
use this experience to potentially take
completely new
directions. And then another piece that
is very important uh has been very
important through the history of math
and science has been to discover
abstract concepts and tools. Uh so for
example you know the idea of calculus
that really sped up the progress of
science uh after it was invented. Uh
similarly with algebra and and uh really
all major branches of mathematics uh
came from the need to abstract some sort
of uh real world process. And then the
value of these abstractions is that that
they speed up both this process of
exploration and also this learning
process that I previously
mentioned. Now if you think of it,
LLM bring something to the uh table
regarding each of these uh criteria. So
for example uh you know if you're doing
a search in a in a very large space of
potential scientific hypothesis and LLM
has inside it a lot of knowledge about
uh what sort of hypothesis have
historically tended to work in science.
And so this knowledge can um potentially
help you um direct this search
process. And then also um you know uh in
this course uh you have seen examples of
LLM agents and in this class you're
going to see more of this. Uh so these
are systems that contain inside them
LLMs as modules but they're also
interacting with the world and they're
learning from experience and and this
experience is uh gathered as as data and
then often uh stuck into the prompt but
sometimes you can even do reinforcement
learning or other kinds of you know
modification of the LLM weights. uh but
the point is that there are all these
established methods for doing learning
combined with uh the use of language
models and that is something that we can
exploit here as
well. Now the use of LLMs for
abstraction this is something that's not
uh well explored yet. This is a really
new idea but I'm going to give you some
evidence um as to why there might be a
lot of things going on here.
And uh there is certainly a lot more to
be done about the use of LLMs in uh
constructing new concepts and new
tools. So I think that u LLM
agents have tremendous promise in
mathematical and scientific discovery.
And the reason is that uh the the so far
as all of these these um ideas go LLM
have a potential to contribute um in in
uh with regards to
each. So this may all seem somewhat
abstract. So I'm going to now jump into
some concrete results. And this lecture
is divided into two pieces. In the first
part, we are going to talk about AI for
mathematical discovery. And then in the
second part, we are going to talk about
AI for scientific discovery. And in each
of these cases, I'm going to show
you some um LLM agents built using quite
different algorithms. But uh but we'll
see that uh these agents
realize many of these ideas that we
talked about in the previous
slide. Okay. So let's talk about AI for
math. Over the last few years, there's
been tremendous interest in this field.
Here's Terry Tao from 2023 talking about
how AI from that year can already
generate suggestive hints and uh help
with the mathematical process. And he
predicted that by
2026 AI can become a trustworthy
co-author in math research papers and in
other fields as well.
Now uh 2026 is not yet here but I would
say that uh this prediction seems very
plausible as of
now. Now um in terms of concrete
systems 01 when it was introduced um one
of
the highlights was that it did really
well in various uh competition
mathematics problems. So um here is a
plot. It shows how 01 does compared to
GBD40. And as you see, accuracy in this
particular competition AM 2024 uh has uh
gone up very
substantially. And then of course last
year my colleagues at Google DeepMind,
they built this system that uh achieved
silver medal level performance at the
IMO. And uh you have already heard us
talk about that uh in this course. So
I'm not going to uh go into further
detail or too much more detail about
that in this talk but uh you you know
that uh it's it's impressive and it uses
a lot of very impressive
machinery. Now one question that uh I
think is important to ask is that is it
all going to be done just with LLMs?
In other words, you know, do you need
any sort of um you know, additional
machinery uh that uh combines LLM with,
for example, actions? You know, this is
really the characteristic that
distinguishes LLM agents from just uh
basic
LLMs. And uh so I would say that um you
know there are certainly still believers
uh in the potential of just LLMs alone
to do everything uh after being trained
on
language. But um I am personally a
little bit skeptical about that
possibility. Now that said you know one
must admit that over the last couple of
years just LLMs have come a long way. Uh
so here is the picture of how you train
an LLM on on u uh for these sorts of
mathematical settings. So you're going
to start with a pre-trained LLM. Then
you're going to train it on you know
math related web docs and then you know
uh problems with step-by-step solutions,
problems with tool integrated solutions
and so on and so forth. And then
ultimately you have this LLM that can
use for example Python APIs and that can
solve math problems.
And this has again as I said uh come a
long way. Uh so for example here is a
problem from the partner math
competition from last year and 01's
response on this problem is actually
very reasonable.
uh and uh as these systems are getting
better and
better, it seems like they're solving
more and more problems uh that are of
this uh nature that are similarly hard
or or
harder. But that said, there is a there
are some fundamental weaknesses of this
neural only approach uh that you'd get
with just a basic LLM.
And the reason is that um or one
fundamental reason is that there is this
issue of data
scarcity. In order to do rigorous
mathematical reasoning, not just
computing answers to wellposed
questions, you need to have a lot of
highquality traces of uh mathematical
reasoning or alternatively you would
need highquality reward functions. And
this is difficult to get just with human
produced
data beyond high school or competition
settings. And then a second reason
fundamentally is that natural language
reasoning is hard to verify. And this is
something that is um that is uh a
fundamental weakness of this language
only
models. And there are even settings
where you can apply this sort of
mathematical reasoning where for example
when you're doing mathematical reasoning
about you know um real world systems and
your the behaviors of these systems have
real consequences. So edge cases are
really critical. So in these cases you
want your mathematical reasoning to be
really robust and rigorous. And
unfortunately,
language-based purely neural
mathematical reasoning tends to not be
this
way. And so, it is entirely possible
that scaling is going to solve all of
these problems, but uh as I said, I'm a
little bit skeptical about this. So in
this talk I'm going to
demonstrate an alternative strategy
which is similar in many ways to alpha
proof which you saw
previously but which is more of a an LLM
agent approach that uh is an alternative
to this sort of purely neural purely
language kind of uh model.
So this alternative involves formal
representations uh just like in alpha
proof. So there's an entire literature
that is um building up that follows this
kind of strategy. And so here what you
do is that rather than just operating in
this space of informal problem
statements and informal solutions, you'd
be first uh doing what is called auto
formalization. So you're going to go
from the informal statement to a formal
statement in a language like lean or
coaul or isabel and lean in particular
is what is used for alpha proof. uh but
uh there are other frameworks like this
as well that have a a very long
history. Now the appeal of these sorts
of formal frameworks is that a proof can
be written in a step-by-step way just
like code and not only that a proof can
be checked. You can check if uh if a
proof uh that you have written in this
formal language actually
implies a certain property that you
started out with. Uh so this uh theorem
that you started out with. And so the
idea is that you would then in the
second phase take this formal problem
statement and then you would be feeding
it to a neural prover which is going to
come up with this sequence of steps
which are also called uh tactics. uh
these these uh rules that you apply. So
these are um tactics and you apply them
one by one and then at the end you get
to uh this uh QED stage uh where you
have nothing left to
prove. And so that that's how uh this
process would work. And the advantage
here is that if you think of the
verification challenge that I mentioned
earlier where you want to check whether
a
claimed proof is actually a proof, this
is something that you can establish uh
relatively easily using a proof
assistant, right? Um and in terms of the
data issues. So the appeal of this kind
of verifiability is that during training
time you can synthetically generate a
very very large number of candidate
proofs and then you can immediately get
feedback or whe on whether or not these
proofs are correct.
So this turns this difficult problem of
proof into this kind of a game playing
task uh which you can approach with uh
really a version of reinforcement
learning and this is what for example
alpha proof did although I'll show here
that you can also take a more LLM based
approach to this problem and um and uh
in fact uh you can build up on these
pre-trained language language models and
only have a pretty thin layer on top of
that and that still does uh quite
interestingly
well. Okay, so just to go into a little
bit more detail about these formal
representations even though you may have
seen this in uh the alpha proof lecture
uh I'll just uh you know quickly recap
uh recapitulate this. So here is a
theorem that uh we are let's say we are
trying to prove and what this says is
that if x is even then x² is even as
well. So the theorem statement over here
says that um x is a natural number and
then it says that x um being even uh
implies x² uh is is also even. So modulo
2 it's uh the the remainder is zero.
So now in order to prove this you are
going to uh apply the sequence of
tactics as I said previously. Now it's
important to note
that the system the the the proof
assistant it has a certain state that
depends on what the original theorem is
and which tactics you have applied so
far. So for example in the beginning you
would have a state that looks like this.
Now just to spell this out what this
means it says that there is one goal
that you currently need to prove and
that goal is that under this context
which is that x is a natural number uh
this is the this is the variable that
you're allowed to use and then this
symbol turn style means that this is
what you need to prove. So this is
basically the theorem that you're
starting out with before you have
applied that
tactic. Now you have the state and then
you apply the tactic which is you can
think of it if you're thinking of this
as you know a reinforcement learning
setup you are applying an action and so
you apply that action and that leads to
a new state and then this state here
looks like this. So this intro tactic
what it does is that it introduces this
this uh new
hypothesis which over here now says that
okay let us assume that x is even along
with uh sorry uh yeah x is even along
with x being a natural number and this
uh property that x is even we are going
to give it a name h and then under this
context which is really like you know
you have now declared a a new variable
which has a certain uh type attached to
to it. Uh so now you are trying to show
that this uh x square is even as well
and then you apply this uh next tactic
which leads to um another state. So
these tactics are written by humans and
they encode various rules of
simplification in in uh mathematics. And
so what you're really doing is that for
each of these rewrite rules that you're
applying the state is changing. So for
example now the state has changed to you
showing that you know if um uh so this
um x modulo 2 * x modulo 2 the the whole
thing modulo 2 that is equal to zero and
then the next rewrite is going to
simplify this and then finally you will
end up with um you know um 0 equals 0
basically and at that point you're going
to hit qed because your goal will just
disappear right so each of these rules
you can think of as simplifying the
state and then at the end ideally you
want to end up in the state where there
are no open goals and at that point you
can end the
proof. So that's what these formal proof
assistants look like really. They're
state machines where you have the proof
state and then these actions which are
these tactics and then they lead to a
new proof state and and your goal really
is to find a sequence of tactics that
take you from this initial state of the
of the of the prover to this qed state
where there are no more goals to be
discharged.
Okay. So now let's uh talk about the two
phases that I mentioned previously. The
autoformmalization phase is something
like this. You're starting with this
informal math statement. there exists an
infinite number of primes and then there
is this uh you know um proof of this as
well in natural language and now you are
applying your auto formalization model
and later I'll talk a little bit about
how this could be done but you know the
version zero of this would be that you
throw a language model at this at this
informal statement and then out comes
this formal theorem right and and so
this one is in lean uh now what this
says uh is that
Um well I won't read this uh thing in
detail uh but uh maybe I can read the
theorem statement uh it says that so for
all n there exist a p such that p is
bigger than greater than equal to n and
then p is also a prime right so that's
how you establish that there's an
infinite number of primes and then the
rest of it is the
proof so then let's assume that you have
done this auto formalization. You have a
formal statement of a theorem and now
you're trying to prove it. So previously
I showed you that there are these
tactics, these simplification rules that
you could apply. But now you can imagine
a search problem where at each state
there is a set of
potential tactics that you could apply
and this leads to the creation of a
search tree and then your goal is to
basically find a path in this tree that
ends up at QED.
Now of course the complexity over here
is that at each point you can have a
very very large number of potential
branches in this tree and then also this
tree can be quite deep right because if
you're talking about really advanced
mathematical theorems uh you could um
end up with proofs that are thousands
and thousands of lines long. And so this
is a far harder problem than any game
playing problem that we have been able
to solve so far.
uh so it's remarkable uh to see the kind
of progress uh that has already happened
in this task over the last few
years. Now alpha proof of course you
have already seen uh you've seen this
picture there's this formalizer network
that does this formalization into formal
problems and then the solver network it
tries to generate these formal proofs.
Uh one big insight was that even
misformalized problems are still helpful
for learning and this sort of proof the
solver network this is being trained
with RL and then one big insight was
that you could complement RL training
with test time RL when you are actually
doing the IMO or any other solving any
other math problem you are uh you could
generate uh you could basically do this
sort of test time RL um on on that um
But again you have you've seen all of
this uh so I'll move
on the approach that I'm going to talk
about today this is uh called copra this
was published in a paper um at the
conference of language models last year
and this is led by my PhD student at UT
Austin Amit
Takur. Now this is the overall picture
of Copra.
it still has this um view of um
interaction between uh an LLM that is
predicting the proof
steps and um the actual proofer that is
executing the the step that is proposed
by the LLM and then and then giving you
a new
state. However, the difference is that
while alpha proof does this sort
of you know uh advanced reinforcement
learning for training. So here you're
just taking this sort of an LLM agent
approach where uh you have a frontier
LLM and the frontier LLM is being
provided the proof state and some
information from the history of the
search so far and then it is making a
prediction as to what's the next step
step that you should take and then you
are taking that step and you're
executing it and then you are getting
back a new state of the of the proof and
then this process is continuing right.
Um now one important thing is that there
is an external search that is going on a
depth first search and then inside the
depth first search you are doing all
this right but it is fundamentally
different in the sense that everything
is in context there is um no actual
adjustment to the way it's happening but
what is interesting is that even with a
relatively small amount of compute this
approach was still uh able to do quite
well and so I think that this strategy
has a lot of long-term promise
for one because it immediately leverages
advances in LLMs as for example you go
from GPD4 to you know um 01 to 03 and to
you know maybe someday GPD5 then uh
you're going to immediately leverage
those advantages uh
advances u and it also has this ability
to integrate natural language and formal
language reasoning uh because ultimately
you're just using an LLM to generate the
the proofs in the
formal formal language but at the same
time the LLM has the ability to do
natural language as well. So this is
something you can you can benefit from
and I'm going to show concrete examples
of this uh in a little
bit. Another thing is that it's also
this strategy is also applicable even if
there is no corpus of training problems.
Now, um, one of the challenges in doing
AI for math once you go outside of
settings such as math competitions is
that you're really trying to solve a new
problem, right? So, if you're a math
researcher, you're trying to solve a new
problem that by design is quite
different from the problems that a lot
of other people have solved previously.
So in such a situation it's a bit
challenging to
um create a corpus of training problems
and then and then u do you know training
of an RL agent. However with an in
context learning agent the appeal is
that uh you can still um use it. The LLM
has inside it a ton of prior knowledge
and that knowledge is something that uh
you could benefit from, right? And the
LLM can for example bring in knowledge
about related problems uh even though
it's not been explicitly trained on them
uh beyond the pre-training
stage. And in the longer run of course
uh the two approaches uh of incontext
learning and and um explicit training
these are not incompatible. So you could
imagine the in context learning agent
being used to generate a lot of
different traces uh by interaction with
the proof assistant and then you could
use them for uh doing fine-tuning.
Now one question that you may have over
here is that well so do I really need to
even have lean in that case couldn't I
just rely on you know the LLM alone and
I would say that the difference here is
that this interaction with the proof
assistant is still providing you know a
very strong form of grounding. So, for
example, if you take a step predicted by
the LLM and then you find that this is
actually an invalid step, you're going
to get that feedback right away from the
proof assistant and you can take that
feedback and you can then stick it back
into the prompt of the LLM and then you
can um you know uh ask it to continue
and then hopefully it'll learn from its
mistake and and carry on. Right? So in
the long run it's possible that once you
have generated a very very very large
number of traces via interaction with
the prover uh maybe you have fine-tuned
your LLM on this all this data and then
the LLM is progressively getting better
and better and uh there is a point
beyond which it just doesn't make any
mistakes uh with this kind of proof.
Maybe we'll get there someday, but we
are still pretty far away from uh that
possibility. So, at least as of now, I
think that um this sort of interaction
between LLM and proof assistant is still
extremely
valuable. Okay, so here is this copra
system in a little bit more detail. Uh
so, what is going on here is that you're
starting with a formal theorem. Uh but
you could also have some informal hints.
You could imagine bringing auto
formalization into this picture as well,
but we didn't. And so the first step is
that you create a prompt based on the
statement of the
theorem. And then you feed it to an um
an an a frontier LLM and you just uh ask
it to generate some potential tactics uh
that would be of interest. And now you
um you do the uh you your model has has
predicted you know a set of one of the
actions uh or or tactics in this case
and then you parse that tactic uh
because it'll be in the form of text. So
now you parse it into a structured
format and then you just execute it via
uh the proof environment the and this
could be lean or or coaul orl and then
after you do that uh in the lucky case
you already hit qed and this is all
done. But uh if you fail, if this uh
tactic is is invalid or there are still
some um some open goals that you still
need to resolve, in that case you uh get
some feedback and then you you know
augment the prompt um and then backtrack
if needed and then you uh we also have
this retrieval phase over here um which
seem to add to the performance. of the
system. Uh and uh here you are also able
to query a lema database and bring in
some relevant lemmas and then add it
back to the prompt. And this process
just continues over and over and over
again until you have uh resolved the
original theorem or alternatively you
have timed
out. So here's the prompt of the system
in a little bit more detail. So here as
you see there is the serialized proof
state and uh here you have you know what
is the goal that you still have to prove
and what are the hypothesis that uh that
are being made. So over here for example
the hypothesis include uh these are the
assumptions you're making right so this
includes x being of type n natural
numbers and then also you know x being
even um and then you have the goal which
is x² modulo 2 is equal to zero
uh we also have this information about
the last step so the way to read this is
that from left to right you are looking
at successive queries to the LLM so the
the first column over here this includes
information about you know what is the
first query that you're making. So the
first thing that you have done so let's
say that you you already have uh made
this um uh decision that you're going to
have this intro tactic right so that's
what created that hypothesis x² modulo 2
equals z so then this is the last step
this is stored in a stack and and uh fed
as part of the prompt
um now uh then uh at this point there
has been no error uh so Then you know
you um get this response from this LLM.
uh after you feed this information that
the next thing that you should do is
rw and then uh now if you try to execute
it you might get you know an error
message uh because a rewrite tactic
failed and then u you know this
information this this error feedback you
send it back to the LLM and then that's
the next query you say that try again
LLM and then the LLM says that okay
let's try apply nack.m mullm mod Right?
Uh now the details of this tactic
doesn't matter. It's you know something
involving modular multiplication but the
point is this is also wrong. So then
again at the next step you get an error
feedback error message and this is
something you stick back into the prompt
and then you make a query again and now
it says oh let's try this uh rewrite
with
nat.mullmod and yay this time it works.
So now you see that the interaction
result doesn't have any error message in
it. It's a success and so um so this is
now put into the stack and so the last
step as you see has changed. It's now
RWN.mmod. So now you're going to make
the try to generate the next step and
then this time it the llm generates this
uh uh rw right and so this is how this
process is going to continue in a
nutshell. you may query the LLM, get a
uh an some error error message and then
stick it back into the prompt and then
continue, right? And and this process
would just um go
on. Okay, so this um evaluation was done
in 2024 actually late 2023. So you know
the world has changed since then but at
least at that point we compared with
GPT4 and found that GPT4 frequently gave
incorrect errors uh incorrect uh proofs
um and uh by contrast this feedback with
um with uh the proof environment uh lean
in this case really helped po Copra and
so even though it was using the same
underlying model the interaction allowed
it to create a correct proof uh in this
case. Here are some experimental
results. You can see the details in in
uh the paper. But uh in this picture on
the x-axis you see the number of queries
and on the y-axis you see the number of
theorems proved. So what we saw over
here is that uh pretty quickly the copra
approach was able to prove a lot of
theorems uh with a relatively small
number of queries. uh whereas um the
other approaches that um that didn't get
that uh
far and here is an evaluation on mini
F2F test. So the absolute numbers are
not great but then you know the amount
of compute we provided copra was also
relatively small. Uh we just allowed you
know 60 queries uh per proof attempt.
Now
um what we saw here was that we got uh
you know quite reasonable performance uh
comparable with the state-of-the-art uh
methods. Now um of course since then the
state-of-the-art on this benchmark has
moved quite a bit. So mini F2F for those
of you who don't know is by the way it's
a compilation of competition mathematics
problems um mostly at the high school
level.
and uh so the so it's of the form that
here is a theorem and come up with a
lean proof. So here what we see is that
there was this um around 29% or or 30%
uh success rate uh which was is uh
behind the current sort but I think one
question would be that if you take this
approach and scale it up then where
would you end up uh and uh there are no
public results on that yet.
So in this talk though I'm going
to go beyond the method that we just
presented which is the basic copra and
um talk about some results that we are
uh we just recently developed. This is
not uh published yet. And here we
are leveraging the ability of LLMs to
abstract and also to uh use natural
language reasoning. Uh because I think
that this is really where the sort of
approach that that we just presented.
This shines because of the tremendous
amount of world knowledge that is stored
inside LLMs. uh we can we can really use
them in a lot more powerful capacity
than just as a predictor of the next
tactic. And so here's a simple a sample
problem. Uh this is from IMO and this is
saying that you know prove that the this
fraction is irreducible for every
natural number
n. So what we'll see is that the copra
approach can be extended a little bit to
um in fact come up with a hierarchical
solution to this
problem. And so uh this will involve
breaking down the problem into sub
problems and then solving
hierarchically. Okay. So how do we do
this? Well, first what we do is that we
ask the LLM to come up with an informal
solution to this
problem. And uh so I don't know if this
uh font is too small to read but
basically what is going on here is that
uh this was fed to 03 a reasoning model
and so it was able to come up with this
you know step-by-step plan. Um so for
example uh you first define the GCD and
then you you know um subtract to
simplify then you apply the uklidian
algorithm and then you conclude
something about the GCD and then you
have the final
conclusion. So then we say that okay so
let's take this informal
decomposition and put it in the context.
Now let's say that um it's our goal to
prove this lema in lean 4 right so this
is the formal statement of the same
problem and we are just saying that
don't try to write the proof okay so
let's just write the sub goals that are
needed to prove this uh but uh we are
doing this conditioned on the informal
proof that we just uh
generated and so here is the the proof
of uh or or here is the decomposition of
this lema. So what you see is that um it
comes up with you know these uh these uh
three sub goals. So first you uh show
that um you know uh this this GCD step
one is true. Um, and it's basically
saying that this GCD of 21 n + 4 * 14 n
+ 3 is the same as the gcd of this, you
know, 14 n + 3 uh * 7 n +
1. So then the there is the second one
then there's the third one and um and
and uh so on and so forth and then
finally you have the main theorem that
combines all of the above.
So the appeal of this sort of
decomposition is
[Applause]
that now this very complex problem has
been simplified into these three sub
problems which are a lot more tractable.
So then then in the next step we then
ask uh copra to solve the sub problems
one by one and what we see is that uh
copra is in fact able to come up with
these uh these proofs of the sub
problems and here we are here are the
proofs again I'm not going to go into
the details of the proofs this is
something that uh you know you have to
stare at for a little bit and and it's
not actually especially
complicated. But then once you have
proven these um these lemas then you
just put them all in the context and
then you also put in the informal proof
and then you ask Copra to prove the the
full
theorem and it is able to do
that but Copra is not able to prove
this. if you were giving it just this um
this entire theorem all in all as one
block and just asked it to
solve. So what we did here is really you
know something that is a a a highly
powerful design pattern in in uh LLM
agents. LLM agents are extraordinarily
flexible.
So with just some variations on the ways
you do prompting, you were able to make
it do very very different things, things
that would take a tremendous amount of
training if you weren't using these
pre-trained models.
And uh so what we did over here is that
we started with a system that was just
designed to be a step-by-step predictor
of a low-level proof and then we made it
do highle reasoning at this more
abstract level right because if you can
think of you can think of these um sub
goals as basically being abstractions of
the of of sub problems and so the LLM is
able to create these abstractions
Right? And once you have created made
use of these
abstractions, your uh proof process
becomes a lot simpler because now you're
able to go
hierarchically. And all of this was
doable without any substantial training.
You were just using the power of
prompting. Right? And to me, this is a
huge revelation. the idea that you can
use the power of language, the power of
all of the stored knowledge you inside
LLMs and then combine that with the sort
of you know higher level algorithmics
where you just you know put together the
informal and formal reasoning steps in
various ways um and change the prompting
strategy and you get something you know
uh that is qualitatively different in in
capability.
Um and now it turns out that uh the lean
feedback here was also really important
uh because at least with 03 mini what we
found is that there were hallucinated
lemas and so on and the grounding that
was provided by the lean theorem prover
was absolutely critical um to solve this
problem. So now I want to uh talk a
little bit about a different application
of the same idea. This is in the context
of formal system verification which is
one of the most practical applications
of rigorous mathematical
reasoning. And so what you're doing in
formal verification is that you're
mathematically modeling a real world
system as a set of
definitions and then you are modeling
system properties as theorems involving
these definitions and then you're
proving these
theorems. These methods have led to
extremely rigorous systems. Systems that
are very difficult to or or almost
impossible to hack. For example, there
was this time in a program organized by
the US Department of
Defense. They used this uh formally
verified Linux kernel called
4 to um and and they put this on a drone
and then they got a red team to try to
attack this drone for a period of six
weeks and they failed right because the
rigor provided by formal verification
was just so
much. Now historically formal
verification has been extremely
expensive and as a result its costs
uh it's not really been widely deployed
because the costs are not justifiable
except in the most safety critical
scenarios. However, with the rise of AI,
especially AI for math, the costbenefit
equation changes quite
drastically and uh now um you can
imagine you know doing not only proofs
of math but proofs of real world systems
uh of for example correctness, security,
performance and so on uh using this
growing generation of AI tools.
So here I'm going to show you a basic
example of this idea. Uh this can be
scaled up substantially with um uh with
more powerful models and more
compute. But uh here what we are going
to do is to give you a very very basic
compiler and then show how to formally
verify its correctness.
Now this is so simple the compiler that
it's almost a joke but um trust me when
you go to more advanced compiler design
the fundamentals don't change it's
really the same sort of idea it's just
that there are there is more
complexity now okay to um do compiler
verification you would need the
following pieces so first of all you
would need to have a notion of um
language and a language consists of a
syntax and a semantics. So syntax is a
grammar that defines the form of the
programs and then semantics are the
rules that define the executions of
programs and then a compiler is
basically a set of rules that translate
programs from one language to another
and then verifications is that you you
prove that the rules preserve
semantics. So here we are going to talk
about a very basic expression language
in which you are allowed to do addition
and multiplication. So this is just
basic arithmetic expressions and this
syntax that you see over here this is in
a language called coaul and
um here it's it looks a lot like lean
it's a similar you know uh dependently
typed functional programming language
and so what you're doing over here is
that you're defining this binary
operator this can be either plus or
times you're defining this notion of an
expression and uh this is saying that it
can be either a constant or a binary
operation. Um and then there is uh there
are some rules that tell you you know
how to
actually evaluate the uh these
expressions you know uh if you if you're
given an expression what will be the
result when you evaluate it and I'm not
going to go into the rules in detail
I'll share the slides and if you're
interested you can uh
um well you can look up many resources
on the on the web but also I'm happy to
answer questions over
offline or actually after this talk.
Okay. So then you define the source
language. So here what you see is that
you can define you know the the rules
that we saw previously they allow you to
define the semantics of quite complex
expressions. So here what you're seeing
is that you know you have const 2. So uh
an an expression can be a constant or a
binary operation or the result of a
binary operation. And you see that you
know this is the result of applying a
binary operation to two expressions you
know and so this is a recursive
definition really and then you are um
getting an expression as as output. Uh
so here what you're seeing is that you
are um you can evaluate various
complicated expressions in this
way. And so now you have to define the
target language right? So this is the a
compiler is a mapping from a source
language to a target language. So now
you have to define the target language
and so what you did over here is that uh
you are defining the target language as
a list of instructions. So a program is
a list of instructions and an
instruction is either this sort of a
constant expression or a binary
operation expression. So one way to see
it is that while the original expression
in the in the source language was
defined in this recursive way in
the in the um target language when you
are interpreting it you are doing it
using a stack. So this is a well-known
idea in programming languages that if
you have a
recursive expression you know let's say
an arithmetic expression then the way
you can execute it is by maintaining a
stack and you can you know keep pushing
the current instruction on the stack and
you can basically uh do this kind of a
low-level you know build up a low-level
machine a stack machine uh actually a
lot of early computers were based on
this idea and then the stack basically
you know keeps pushing
new things on it and uh and and then you
pop and and then you read the value that
was just
popped.
So while very basic, it still captures a
lot of important programming language
concepts. Now the point is that uh I
want to believe that uh the mapping that
I would do between these two
representations is actually correct. But
of course first I have to uh define the
compiler and so this is the compiler. So
what this says is that I am going to you
know take my input expression in the
source language and then I'm going to do
a pattern matching. I'm going to
consider these two cases either when
it's a constant or when it's a binary
operation and in each of these cases I'm
going to you know um generate a target
language program. So in the target
language program the entire sequence of
instructions is just written down as a
list. Now it's when you are executing
the program that you are maintaining a
stack right that's when you are doing
you know all of the kind of modeling the
recussion. uh but in the program itself
you are just doing this kind of a uh you
you're generating the instructions from
E2 you're generating the instructions
from E1 and then you are sticking this B
and then you are just you know building
up a stack uh with or or a sequence of
instructions uh with uh with all of
this. So for example you know if you
started with this expression you know b
plus con 2 con 3. So this is you know 2
+ 3 is that's really the expression and
so then in the in the lower level
language it's going to look like this.
So then you have to define this
correctness theorem which says that for
all E in the s all programs all
expressions E in the source language
upon compiling this expression you get
something that when you execute it in
the programming languages semantics you
get the same thing as if you um if you
evaluated the
original expression in the source
languages semantics right so these two
are the are the
same Now it turns out that copra cannot
prove this theorem just in one shot. So
what you do instead is that you ask the
LLM again think of the IMO example that
I showed this is uh quite similar. So
you ask the LLM to invent a lema an
intermediate goal. So um the LLM goes
ahead and thinks for a while and this is
01 here and it comes up with this
intermediate lema uh which basically
says that rather than trying to
prove the entire compiler correct what
you instead do is that you just show you
know one
step of compilation like for one um one
sub expression uh that's going to be
correct.
Uh so so basically that's the target
theorem. The auxiliary lema is saying
that you can compile you know one
instruction correctly first. And so this
is really just um simplifying the
problem breaking it down in a
step-by-step way and and then we ask
Copra to come up with a proof of this
one instruction and it's able to uh
which is
fantastic. But uh then what we can do is
just in the way we did previously we
stick this back uh we we take this proof
give it to the the copra agent uh put it
in the prompt and then ask it to you
know prove the entire theorem correct
and it's now able to do
this.
So that's what I uh have on this
particular topic. Uh in summary, I would
say that mathematical discovery with LLM
agents is extremely promising.
I think that you can go a very long
distance with uh just uh you know in
context learning. uh but uh you want to
have the proof assistant feedback for
proper grounding and there is a lot of
you know higher level agent design that
you can do where you can
combine agents that are doing you know
for example formalization with agents
that are doing hierarchical planning
with agents that are doing low-level uh
stuff low-level proof generation
um and there is uh this is a very new
space there is a lot to be done over
here
Now you know one question again going
back to something we asked
previously. Can you get rid of this
interaction by just uh pushing the whole
thing to training? Maybe you know you
generate a lot of training
data in this way uh by interaction with
the proofer and then you you know um
just continue training the LLM with
those traces and then at some point the
LLM just gets good enough. We are not
there yet. Uh but maybe this is a world
that we can get to someday. Um but
currently um we have to have these sorts
of agent
architectures. Now there's this uh paper
uh several of us uh recently wrote and
you may have seen a reference to this
paper previously. Uh Caillou is the lead
author of this um and uh Dawn was the
leader of the overall effort. uh uh but
if you are curious about this area, you
want to uh you know know more about you
know specific challenges road maps then
I would recommend uh that you go and
look at this
paper. Um I had a few things to say
about open challenges but I'm going to
skip those in the interest of time and
I'm going to move on to
the uh next topic which is uh AI for
scientific uh discovery uh
because I want to emphasize that this
idea of LLM agents this has a lot of
value in this sort of deductive
mathematics where you are starting with
a set of principles set of axioms
definitions
and then you are proving statements in a
step-by-step way. But it also has
tremendous potential in empirical
discovery which is what happens in most
of the natural sciences where you are uh
starting with data and then you are
trying to fit
um you know some hypothesis uh or or
some uh some experimental cla or some
some claims to this data. Um now we'll
see that this is also a place where the
abstraction abilities of LLMs uh play a
potentially very interesting
role. Okay. So very quickly
um this is what a natural science
process looks like. you know, you choose
a research question, you generate some
hypothesis, you uh do an experimental
setup, you collect some data, you do
some analysis of the data, you interpret
the data, and then you report to the
community, right? And
um and so uh just as an example of this,
you know, if you think of the uh world
of
astronomy, back in the day, there was
this problem uh that was uh observed
which is that people believed that the
the earth was the center of the solar
system, but then some of the planets
appear to move backward. And so this led
to this creation of this new hypothesis
that in fact we have a heliocentric
model and then this led to the creation
uh the collection of more data. Uh Taiko
Brahe in particular observed Mars and
then uh came up with a whole bunch of
precise measurements of the planet's
positions.
um and then um Kepler chose to analyze
this data and then fit a wide variety of
geometric shapes to this data and then
he came up with this Kepler's third law.
Um and then this eventually led to uh
Newton's law of gravitation. Uh so there
was this process that happened in
science which uh involved trading in
abstractions you know uh seeing some
data and then coming up with this uh
this this law in terms of abstract
principles uh but then you know further
generalizing it into a law that was even
more
explanatory. So I think that LLM agents
have tremendous potential in automating
a lot of pieces of this pipeline and in
particular here we are going to focus on
the problem of symbolic regression which
is uh the task of coming up with
equations based on empirical
observations.
Uh so for
example an instance of that would be
that if you were given these
measurements of planet
Mars and then uh you wanted to discover
Kepler's law how do you do that right
from the
data now one would think that LMS would
not be a great fit for this problem
because the data is just really low
level right this is just a bunch of
numbers however it turns Turns out uh
that LLMs uh do have a tremendous
potential over here in the sense that uh
they can bring in prior scientific
knowledge into the picture. What you
have to do though is that you have to
complement the use of LLMs with the use
of other machinery that is able to for
example evaluate hypothesis on the data
and uh give you uh some notion of how
well it performed.
So once you have that kind of a
mechanism for evaluating LLM generated
hypothesis, you can create an agentic
loop where you have more and more
feedback going to the LLM and then uh
you know this process of hypothesis
generation is left to the LLM whereas
you know hypothesis evaluation is done
by some some other um entity and if you
think of it it's not fundamentally
different from the way we use lean or or
the proof assistant in the previous part
of the
lecture. So, uh
the one of the most established
approaches to symbolic regression is
genetic programming and the here are
some visualizations from a system called
Pyer which is quite popular in this
space. And so what's going on here is
that you have a pool of candidate
expressions, candidate equations being
maintained and then you have um mutation
and crossover operations being applied
to those and then uh you know you are
generating you're updating this this
pool of expressions using feedback from
a separate machinery that is evaluating
these expressions and telling you you
know how good is the loss, how well does
this uh match the match the reality that
is there in the
data. So uh this has had a lot of
impact. Uh there are applications in you
know physics and uh other areas as well.
And um so here are some example papers.
Um so um one thing that's interesting is
that if you just imagine how does this
process
of genetic programming go on. So there
is this pool of expressions that is
being evolved. And so what you see is
that there are these uh you know islands
of expressions. So these clusters which
uh contain expressions that are of um
that have something in common between
them. Um so
the one way to think about how LLMs are
relevant is that these clusters or
islands of expressions these capture
various kinds of you know various
classes of functions. So for example you
know in this red one over here you may
have exponential functions. Um in this
case you may have trigonometric
functions uh where you have the
cosiness and so so one way to imagine
this is that an LLM um looking at these
these uh expressions because LLMs are
good at coding and associating code with
natural language could perhaps come up
with you know some explanation of what
this piece of code this expression is
actually doing right and that's the idea
of abstraction that we are going to
Okay. Uh so this paper uh was at Nurips
last year and uh co-led by Arya Gley who
was an undergrad at UT and Aurva Seagal
who's a PhD student um at UT and uh
so so the starting point here is that we
want to do this kind of concept
abstraction and so um what we want to be
able to do is that we want to look at
you know these variety of laws uh which
come from very different contexts. But
then, you know, we should be able to
look at this and kind of tell that
what's going on here is that you have,
you know, this power law thing going on.
All right. Um, and uh, so, uh, the other
thing we want to do is that we want to
use background knowledge that was
created by a physicist or that's there
inside an LLM. Um so for example here
you have you know an LLM uh a a concept
that has been produced which is that you
know wave strain diminishes as distance
increases. This is a let's say property
of you know the
um of black holes and so you want to be
able to
associate this kind of um information
you know this is a piece of common sense
knowledge to equations. Um so this
equation for example satisfies these
properties but um this is you want to
create a mapping between these two
things and because you know if you
imagine how the scientific process is
ongoing so let's say you have an AI that
is predicting equations based on data
you also want it to be conditioned on
this sort of highle knowledge that is
being given by a human expert right and
so so you want to have this association
between between code that is these
equations and and
language.
Um
so the way we set up this symbolic
regression problem using um LLMs is
something like this that we
imagine that um and and actually here
it's not just LLMs it's more like you
know a combination of LLMs and this sort
of um abstraction into high level
concepts uh and and so we imagine that
there is this universe of highle
concepts. So for example you know wave
strain diminishes as distance increases
or power laws or cinosidal functions
these are sort of highle ideas that we
have in our head and there is a notion
of a data set which is the concrete data
uh that you want to fit and then you
have a space of programmatic hypothesis.
This this is for example the you know
the the landscape of equation or the set
of equations expressible in Python or or
you know in some restricted DSL inside
Python and then what you're saying is
that you want to jointly infer given the
data uh this uh distribution over pi
which is you know likely hypothesis and
likely concepts. So you don't want to
just get likely programs given the data
which would be the goal of traditional
symbolic regression. You want to get
both the programs and also the kinds of
concepts that they represent because
ultimately you want to explain these
programs to a human uh scientist or
alternatively maybe you know this joint
distribution gives you more more
information than if you just operated in
the program
space. And so this you can factoriize in
this way. And then um it uh turns out
that you know um the way to think about
it is that uh p of d given pi is
basically saying that if I have a
particular program pi what is
the likelihood of the data. So you know
how well does the program explain the
data? In order to find this, you just
execute the program, right? And see what
kinds of results come out and if it what
the likelihood of the data set is. And
uh P of pi given C is basically telling
telling you that okay here are these um
these uh con here is a concept that I
have. So let's say I'm thinking about
power laws. Okay. So conditioned on this
concept that I'm thinking about power
laws. what is the probability of this
program that uh you know this piece of
code right uh to what extent does this
piece of code represent a power law and
this is something that an LLM has
background knowledge inside it to do and
then finally I have this PFC which is a
prior concepts and this is also
something that an LLM knows that you
know I have seen the literature of let's
say physics until this point so what is
the likelihood of this concept concept,
right? Um
so all of this together gives you
ultimately the ability to infer uh both
um a distribution over a distribution
over both programs and and
concepts. Now in order to really
implement this uh this is the loop that
we came up with. Uh so this follows the
basic structure of an evolutionary
algorithm but it does this sort of uh
you know this sort of basian concept
learning thing uh guided by LLMs on on
top of
that and so operationally the way to
think about it is that you have a like
in any evolutionary algorithm you're
maintaining a population of hypothesis
or
programs and then at this point you have
a choice of doing you know um evolution
either guided by the classical symbolic
method where you're doing some random
tweaks to the abstract syntax tree of
the program or alternatively you are
doing this LLM guided evolution where
you are saying that here is a concept
here is a program that I have and I want
to generate a new program and when
you're doing that you are being guided
by this concept library which tells you
that you know these are the concepts
that I'm thinking about right now right
so power laws seem really good uh really
well suited to this condition uh this
concept or or this setting or you know
maybe um uh trigonometric functions seem
especially well suited to this setting
and so on right so you are feeding all
of that to this LLM guided evolution
process and that allows you to you know
basically mutate the current
programs into new
programs and then after you do that you
are like in the usual evolutionary way
you are identifying the best candidates
in in this population. Um and so this is
where you use the fitness function which
is you know how well do your do your um
does your uh hypothesis pool explain the
data that you have right and this is
where that p of d given pi that comes in
um and so this is a little bit more
detail about how the hypothesis
evaluation evolution works. Uh so you
know you start with this initialization
initial program population and then
you're evaluating you're getting the
best program you're mutating or crossing
over and then you are um you're
replacing the oldest program and then
this process just carries on uh for a
while. Uh so the important thing over
here is that you are using the LLM for
implementing this mutation and crossover
operations. So in particular rather than
you know um in a classical genetic
algorithm what's going to happen is that
you're given the a and you're going to
say that okay swap out this sub tree by
a different sub tree. Now you're going
to say that I'm going to ask the LLM to
rewrite the program into something. And
this idea was also used in um the fund
search paper from uh deep mind last
year. And uh fun search uh has been very
successful. The way in which the this
laser work differs from fun search uh is
fundamental in its use of this concept
library. But a lot of the other ideas
are are uh closely related.
Um so this is just to highlight you know
the difference between the symbolic
crossover versus the LLM crossover. So
in this case the LLM is basically doing
all this. Uh it's being given a
crossover prompt and then it's given
some formatting instructions and then
it's generating the new
expression. So after you do this um
there is the so you have evolved your
hypothesis. So now you have this new
pool and now you also evolve your
concept library. And so the concept
library uh uh this evolution process has
these two stages. So first you know you
take your new programs that you've
created your new program pool and now
you're asking the LLM to abstract this
into these sort of natural language
highle descriptions. So for example here
the LLM is telling you that oh this
equation represents exponential growth
or
decay. And then the LLM uh the concept
evolution process is just like the
hypothesis or program evaluation
evolution process except it now uses
this uh u you know an LLM to basically u
combine mash up these different concepts
into a new concept. So for example here
you see that you know exponential growth
decay this is one concept another
concept says depend on depends on
temperature and our LLM because it has
all this knowledge about all sorts of
concepts relevant in physics it comes up
with this idea that oh you know this uh
should be a Boltzman distribution this
is a useful concept to have and then
this is going to influence the
hypothesis evolution which is going to
influence concept abstraction and
evolution and this loop will
continue. So um one way to uh visualize
this is that after the first phase when
you have done this hypothesis evolution
you may have these you know islands of
different kinds of
expressions. Now in the uh
concept generation process concept
discovery process uh you're going to get
these you know natural language
descriptions of these different islands.
So this is sinosidal trends, this is
power law trends, this is linear trends,
this is exponential trends and so on.
And um then um what we found is that the
use of this sort of a highle concept
library helped us in this equation
discovery process. So we evaluated this
on this task of you know equation
discovery um or discovering fineman
equations just given the the uh prompt
that so there was the data but then
there was a prompt that uh told you you
know which chapter you were looking at
and and so on. And so what we found is
that uh this uh approach proved more
effective than a version where you were
just using either pure genetic
programming or one where uh you were not
using uh any kind of concept learning.
And um so the so uh it turns out that
even with local language models when we
didn't use a frontier model uh we were
still able to outperform uh this uh
genetic programming approach and um and
the overall finding was that uh and you
can find more details in the paper is
that the use of this sort of highle
concepts generated by the LLM it
accelerates uh
discovery. Now one appeal of this sort
of um
um LLM based approach is that it can
very naturally take in user provided
hints. So in this case uh we uh gave the
uh the um algorithm some hints which was
you know uh this is the kind of equation
you are looking at. Uh so in the
previous uh experiments actually we did
not have hints. So this was just you
know purely based on data but then uh in
this case we had hints and then we found
that hints actually uh provided uh some
benefits. So on the x-axis here you have
the number of iterations on the y-axis
you have the you know the fraction of
equation solved and then we found that
the use of the hint said it provided a
modest benefit uh at least earlier on in
the process.
So here is an example of this in action.
Uh so um here this is the classic
kulum's law and then um pyer is this
genetic programming approach and um it
gave this very unwieldy kind of
expression um that it turns out is
equivalent to the ground truth
expression but it required a lot of
simplification uh for you to it would
require a lot of simplification for you
to go from here to the ground truth
whereas the laser approach approach uh
is able to uh basically
uh because of the uh you know some of
the knowledge that is there in the LLM
it's able to you know reduce to ground
truth after four steps of simplification
now you could say wait a second isn't
the LLM cheating because it already has
kulum's law in its mind so how do you
know that this is not just you know
leakage and of course in this case there
is that possibility but that said I
would say that you know the attraction
here is that the input to the system is
just this data right uh it's just the
input output values uh for that would
result from kulum's law and it's a very
low-level kind of input the fact that it
was able to fit this to kulum's law is
is kind of interesting but that said we
also did other experiments on synthetic
data uh where you just manufactured a
completely uh weird equation and a weird
data set uh coming from that equation
and then asked the system to to
regenerate this and we found that there
were substantial benefits even in that
case. So um here is some information
about some of the concepts that you
ended up getting from from laser. So you
see there is stuff like you know good
mathematical expressions exhibit
symmetry or regularity but that said
there were also some expressions that
were really um that didn't really seem
to mean
anything. Um but at the same time you
know there is no guarantee about the
quality of the concepts. This is all
natural language at this point and
interesting possibility is to use some
kind of a formal language to describe
the the highle concepts.
Now we also use this in a new discovery
problem because we were u also worried
about the possibility of this being an
artifact of leakage in case of standard
benchmarks like discovering fineman
equations and so we used this uh method
to come up with a new scaling law for
LLMs and um so here what you see is um
the so-called chinchila law so this is a
law that was postulated in a deep mind
paper from a few years back. And so here
basically what you're trying to do is to
predict the loss of the LLM, you know,
based on um these various
hyperparameters. And so this was the
law. So you postulate a scaling law, you
measure model loss with respect to
hyperparameters and then you fit scaling
law to data set. And in order to do
this, of course, you would need to have
a data set where you have a lot of
values of these hyperparameters and
corresponding uh accuracy values for the
LLM. Now, we did the same thing with
laser
um rather than fitting a hand fitted law
which was done in the in the chinchilla
paper, right? So, they basically
postulated a law like this and then they
fit the parameters. But by contrast,
what we did is that we just asked laser
to go find it. And laser was able to
come up with this sort of a law where um
we also had this you know parameter
called number of shots which is that if
you're doing prediction you know what is
the number of examples that you're
giving it in context. Um and uh this in
this parameter is available in some of
these data sets right and so what we
found is that there was this interesting
kind of law that uh came up. Now this is
just you know one example. It's not
really uh very comprehensive yet but
this just shows that you can make these
kinds of new discoveries using using
this uh law. And so basically if you
interpret this, the way to think about
it is that a large number of shots gives
poor results for low capability models.
But then once the models pass a
capability threshold, then having more
shots, right? And this is sort of a
common sense linguistic interpretation
of the law that came
out. So
um you know um you can also do something
after this. So if you're thinking about
thinking of yourself as an LL and
scaling law person, you start with the
chinchilla law from the previous paper
and then you say okay you know maybe I
should bring in this insight about shots
into the chinchilla law combine the old
chinchilla law with this new discovery
that was made by laser and then you find
that uh this modified chinchilla
actually is able to do better than both
the old chinchilla and also the the you
know the laser itself and so this is
kind of interesting that um and shows
that you know this discovery process
using LLM agents and this is very much
an agent right this is not just a
oneshot LLM you're using an LLM combined
with this various other tools um and uh
so what you are getting out of this
is can influence human discovery as well
and lead to something that is greater
than the sum of the parts
So in the interest of time I'm going to
skip uh this next bit. Uh but uh what I
said there is that these ideas can also
be applied to settings where you have
visual highdimensional inputs because
now we have vision language models as
well. So you can uh go crazy and and
build these kinds of evolution based
agents um where you have VLMs as part of
the story. And uh I I'm extremely
optimistic about uh this direction. So
in summary, I would say that LLM
directed evolution is a powerful tool
for empirical science. And this point
has already been made uh previously by
fun search. But now you know we see that
we can make it even more powerful with
these um ideas of abstraction that are
uh that that LLMs can give you basically
for free. And uh even you know this can
be even extended to visual settings
where you have um to use now vision
language models but hey they're coming a
long way they have come a long way and
uh importantly the abstraction abilities
of LLMs can also be really helpful
here open challenges you know
verification of hypothesis and concepts
concept representations that go beyond
natural
language scaling to larger search spaces
input dimensions and then you even going
beyond hypothesis generation to other
parts of the scientific discovery
process. But at the end though I am very
optimistic
that LLM agents not just LLMs but these
kinds of agentic workflows where you
have combinations of LLM
queries as well as other kinds of
machinery u they can be extremely
powerful in scientific discovery. They
can help you come up with new scientific
hypothesis and uh even do experiment
design and also as we saw in
mathematical discovery they can be
supremely powerful and again we are just
in the early stages of uh what I think
uh this research line of research will
end up being. Um and this can have
applications in uh in math, in science,
in engineering as you saw the formal
verification application, you know,
building rigorous systems. Um so the
future is is very bright. And with that,
uh I'll end. I want to thank all my
collaborators and funders. Uh, and I'm
happy to take questions.